A Guide to the Records of the William H. Leighty, Deputy Secretary of Transportation, 1984-1990
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of William H. Leighty, Deputy Secretary of Transportation, 1984-1990
The Library of Virginia
50129
3 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
William H. Leighty, 2004 Millington Dr., Henrico, VA 23238, date of gift 3 June 2011; accessioned 12 September 2011.
Historical Information
In 1986 Governor Gerald L. Baliles (1986-1990) named William H. Leighty Deputy Secretary of Transportation. Leighty served as served as policy adviser to the Governor on transportation-related issues and oversaw operation of seven state agencies--Departments of Transportation, Aviation, Motor Vehicles, Emergency Services, Military Affairs, Fire Programs and Virginia Port Authority. Leighty also served as Chief of Staff to Governors Mark R. Warner and Tim Kaine.
The Commission on Virginia's Transportation in the Twenty-First Century was created by Senate Joint Resolution 10 of 1986 to study future needs and financing of transportation for the Commonwealth. The Commission was composed of six (6) house of Delegate member's appointed by the Speaker, four (4) Senate members appointed by the Committee on Privileges and Elections, fourteen (14) members at large appointed by the Governor and former Gorvernors of the Commonwealth.
The Commission was authorized to carry out its work in two phases. The first phase required that the Commission determine the most critical transportation needs and determine what legal changes would be necessary to establish separate funds for highway maintenance and construction. The second phase required the Commission to study in detail alternatives for planning and financing the entire transportation system including rail, air and water transportation. The second phase was also charged with addressing the role of local government in financing various transportation projects and the discovery of alternative methods of raising funds such as tolls, dedicated revenues and transportation districts.
Senate Joint Resolution Number 148 of 1987 further outlined phase two of the Commissions responsibilities. The Commission had four areas of specific concerns: (1) builder contributions to off-site road improvements; (2) development impact fees; (3) granting to local governments increased statutory authority to consider the capacity of local roads and other public facilities when rendering land use decisions such as rezoning; and (4) proposals to grant to local units of government expanded power to construct and control local roads.
The Commission was charged with completing its first phase of work and submitting a report with recommendations to Governor and General Assembly no later than August 1, 1986. The first phase of the report served as the basis for action on transportation needs taken by the Special Session of the General Assembly on September of 1986. The second phase and report with recommendations had a scheduled completion date of December 1, 1987.
Scope and Content
This collection contains Deputy Secretary William H. Leighty's briefing binders, memorandums, minutes and reports concerning transportation legislation and Governor Gerald Baliles' (1986-1990) Commission on Transportation in the Twenty-First Century. In September 1986 Governor Baliles convened a special session of the General Assembly that passed a 12-year, $12 billion transportation package to modernize the state's roads, seaports, airports, and mass transit, partially funded by a half cent increase in the sales tax. Additional records document the implementation of this legislation including a list of transporation week events in September 1987. Also included are miscellaneous state government reform reports.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Records, 1984-1990
Contents List
- I. Records, 1984-1990., Extent: 3 cubic feet (3 boxes). (Box 1-3)
  Original order maintained
  - Briefing Binder on Senate Bill 79 (1986), 1986. (Box 1)
  - Briefing Binder on Transportation Special Session of the General Assembly, September 1986. (Box 1)
  - Bill Book (Transportation Special Session Legislation), 1986. (Box 1)
  - Commission on Transportation in the Twenty-First Century (reports, memorandums, memorandums, 1985-1986. (Box 2)
  - Commission on Transportation in the Twenty-First Century (strategic implementation binder), 1986. (Box 2)
  - Transportation Commission Briefing Manual for Members of the General Assembly (Commission on Transportation in the Twenty-First Century), 1 August 1986. (Box 2)
  - Transportation Commission Briefing Manual for Members of the General Assembly (Commission on Transportation in the Twenty-First Century), December 1987. (Box 2)
  - Commission on Transportation in the Twenty-First Century (Phase II), 1987. (Box 1)
  - Briefing Book, Transportation Week, September 1987. (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Reports and Documents, 1984-1990. (Box 3)